City Official's Idea to House Homeless: A Cruise liner
A San Francisco Bay Area city official wants to explore the possibility of using a cruise ship
to house up to 1,000 homeless people amid a high cost of living and a shortage of housing.
Oakland City Council President Rebecca Kaplan told a council meeting that the ship would be brought to the Port of Oakland.
Port officials, however, said the move would be unfeasible.
“We respect President Kaplan's desire to address homelessness, but the Port of Oakland docks are designed to work cargo ships; there isn't the infrastructure to dock a cruise ship,” port spokesman Mike Zampa said.
The port is among the 10 busiest in the nation, and safety and security issues in the federally regulated facilities would make residential uses unviable, according to Zampa.
Homelessness has spiked in Oakland in the past two years, with the number of unsheltered people increasing from 1,900 to more than 3,000 people.
Kaplan said she has been contacted by cruise ship companies about providing a ship for emergency housing,
and that the companies were reaching out to the Port of Oakland about what options exist to park a ship at the port.
She didn't provide further details on those companies.
Kaplan also said she plans to present a proposal to the council that will be no or low cost to the city.
This is because the city would not have to pay for the cruise ship, and its future residents would pay for rooms based on their income.
“Cruise ships have been used for emergency housing after natural disasters and for extra housing for things like the Olympics.
It could be a great way to house a lot of people quickly,” Kaplan said.
She compared her vision for an Oakland cruise ship to something like the Queen Mary in Long Beach in Southern California.
The 1936 ocean liner is now a floating hotel with 347 rooms. “It could be used like that,” Kaplan said. “But as affordable housing instead of a hotel.”